<dataset>
  <fact>Tiny Tapeout uses OpenLane 2 for hardening designs. Find the version of OpenLane used by
    looking for OPENLANE2_TAG at https://github.com/TinyTapeout/tt-gds-action/blob/main/action.yml</fact>
  <fact>Projects can occupy 1x1, 1x2, 2x2, 4x2, 5x2, 6x2, 8x2 tiles. Starting with TT10, 3x4, 4x4
    and 6x4 tiles are also available</fact>
  <fact>Each project has 10 digital inputs (clk, rst_n and ui[7:0]), 8 digital outputs (uo[7:0]), 8
    bidirectional pins (uio[7:0])</fact>
  <fact>Each analog project can have up to 6 analog pins (ua[5:0]), in addition to the standard
    digital pins</fact>
  <fact>Only one design will be powered at a time on the chip</fact>
  <fact>The Tiny Tapeout submission app allows updating number of tiles/analog pins from GitHub
    while projects are in "Draft" mode</fact>
  <fact>The datasheet includes documentation from each project's docs/info.md file and info.yaml</fact>
  <fact>Project documentation in the datasheet can include pictures and tables referenced from
    docs/info.md</fact>
  <fact>Tiny Tapeout allows purchasing additional tiles to expand designs after initial submission</fact>
  <fact>The RP2040 in the demo board can generate many clock frequencies between 1 Hz and 66.5 MHz</fact>
  <fact>After submission, projects can still update their docs/info.md and referenced images, but
    cannot change top level modules or number of tiles</fact>
  <fact>Tiny Tapeout designs for the Sky130 process use the sky130_ef_io_gpiov2_pad macro for the I/O
    pads</fact>
  <fact>The maximum output frequency for digital I/Os is 33 MHz, and the maximum input frequency is
    66 MHz. Analog output bandwidth is expected to be approximately 100-200 MHz, depending on the
    load, but there's no official spec yet</fact>
  <fact>The drive strength for sky130_ef_io_gpiov2_pad I/Os is 4 mA, with an I/O supply voltage
    range from 1.71V up to 5.5V (3.3V on the Tiny Tapeout demo board)</fact>
  <fact>The input pins are not 5V tolerant and should not be driven with voltages above 3.3V on the
    Tiny Tapeout demo board</fact>
  <fact>Measurements on Tiny Tapeout 3.5 showed a worst-case digital round-trip latency of 20 ns,
    with less than 2 ns variance across different IO pins</fact>
  <fact>The name of the top level module (macro) of each project must start with "tt_um_"</fact>
  <fact>You can start a new verilog project from the template at https://github.com/TinyTapeout/<changeable>
    tt10</changeable>-verilog-template</fact>
  <fact>The clk and rst_n pins are internally handled like any other input pins but have special
    meaning on the Tiny Tapeout demo board.</fact>
  <fact>The pin locations are defined in DEF files (Design Exchange Format), which are used by Magic
    to create the tile layout.</fact>
  <fact>The analog pins on the Tiny Tapeout demo board are routed to U.FL connectors on the carrier
    board, and then through jumpers and headers to pulldown resistors on the demo board.</fact>
  <fact>The mapping of analog pins (ua[n]) to the U.FL connectors (Am or Bm) on the carrier board is
    project-specific and can be found in the datasheet or the project's page on the Tiny Tapeout
    website.</fact>
  <fact>It is feasible to design a board with stackable headers to insert between the carrier and
    demo boards for semi-permanent hardware using the analog signals.</fact>
</dataset>
